A Guide to the Engravings of George Washington, 1834-1874, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Engravings of George Washington 1834-1874, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10213-c
27 engravings and lithographs
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the Library from Colburn & Tegg, Hollis N.Y. in 1977.
Biographical/Historical Information
George Washington: born at his father's plantation on Popes Creek in Westmoreland County, Virginia, on February 22, 1732; commander of the Continental Army June 1775-December 23, 1783; president of the Constitutional Convention; served two terms as President, 1789-1797; died December 14, 1799 at Mount Vernon.
Martha Washington: born on June 2, 1731, at Chestnut Grove Plantation in New Kent Country, Virginia; married Daniel Parke Custis, 1749; married George Washington at her home, White House, on January 6, 1759; died May 22, 1802.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 27 engravings and lithographs of George Washington, Martha Washington, the Washington family and Mount Vernon.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series: Series I: George Washington; Series II: Martha Washington; and, Series III: Washington Family and Mount Vernon. Each series is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Series I: George Washington
  - "The national portrait gallery of distinguished Americans, 1834" 1834 (Folder 1)
    Engraving of medal surrounded by text.
  - Engraving "from the original painting by Chappell, in the possession of the publishers" 1870 (Folder 2)
    Published by Johnson, Fry & Co., Publishers, New York.
  - Engraving "from the original painting by Chappell, in the possession of the publishers" 1871 (Folder 3)
  - "The bivouac at Monmouth. From the original picture by A. Chappell, in the possession of the publishers." 1874 (Folder 4)
    Published by Johnson, Wilson & Co., Publishers, New York.
  - "Washington taking command of the army. From the original picture by Chappel, in the possession of the publishers." 1874 (Folder 5)
  - "Valley Forge--Washington & Lafayette." 1874 (Folder 6)
  - Engraving by Edwards, after Gilbert Stuart n.d. (Folder 7)
    Within ornamental border and above vignette of the Battle of Trenton. Published by Virtue & Yorston, New York.
  - Engraving by A. B. Walter, after Gilbert Stuart n.d. (Folder 8)
    Published by J. C. McCurdy & Co., New York.
  - Lithograph; after Gilbert Stuart. n.d. (Folder 9)
  - Engraving by W. Humphreys, after Gilbert Stuart. n.d. (Folder 10)
    Published by William Mackenzie, London, Edinburgh & Glasgow.
  - Engraving, after Gilbert Stuart n.d. (Folder 11)
    Published by H. H. Hall's Sons, New York
  - Engraving "from the original portrait by Stuart in the Boston Athenaeum" n.d. (Folder 12)
    Published by Johnson, Wilson & Co. Publishers, New York
  - Engraving n.d. (Folder 13)
    After Trumbull?
  - Engraving by J. C. Buttre, after Gilbert Stuart. n.d. (Folder 14)
  - Engraving by G. R. Hall after Gilbert Stuart n.d. (Folder 15)
    Published by Virtue & Yorston, New York.
  - Engraving "by A. B. Durand from the full length portrait by Col. Trumbull belonging to Yale College" n.d. (Folder 16)
  - "Washington's head quarters near Monmouth" n.d. (Folder 17)
  - "Washington crossing the Delaware" Engraved by J. Rogers, after E. Leutze. n.d. (Folder 18)
- Series II: Martha Washington
  - Engraving "from the original painting by Chappel in the possession of the publishers. 1872 (Folder 19)
    Published by Johnson, Fry & Co Publishers, New York.
  - Engraving by J. C. Buttre, after Woolaston n.d. (Folder 20)
  - Engraving by J. C. Buttre, "from Stuart's picture" n.d. (Folder 21)
  - Engraving "by J. H. Longacre from an original miniature by Robertson, in possession of G. W. E. Custis, Esq." n.d. (Folder 22)
  - Engraving "by J. H. Longacre from an original miniature by Robertson, in possession of G. W. E. Custis, Esq." n.d. (Folder 23)
    Within ornamental frame border.
  - Engraving by J. C. Buttre, after Stuart n.d. (Folder 24)
- Series III: Washington family and Mount Vernon
  - Engraving by A. B. Walter, after F. Schell. n.d., Published by John Dainty, Philadelphia. (Folder 25)
  - Engraving "for the 'Eclectic' by Geo. F. Petrie, N.Y." n.d. (Folder 26)
  - Engraving by Pierson n.d. (Folder 27)